Guide to the John Lakin Brasher Papers, 1857-1993 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Lakin Brasher papers 1857-1993 and undated
Brasher, John Lakin, 1868-1971
45 linear feet Extent: 33,750 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00146
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Publication of addition 2013-0075 requires special permission until Dec 31, 2023.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of John Lakin Brasher (1868-1971), preacher, evangelist, and leader of the Holiness movement, were donated to the Rubenstein Library by The Brasher Heritage Corporation in 1981, with later additions in 1997, 1998, 2004, and 2013.
Biographical Note
1868, July 20 Born at Clear Creek, Etowah County, Alabama; baptized at Alabama Annual Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church during same year
1886 Joined Clear Creek Methodist Episcopal Church
1889 Licensed to preach
1890, Dec. 21 Married Minnie Eunice Moore in Alabama of Gallant, Alabama
1891 Joined Alabama Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church
1892-1896 Four years of ministry on Wedowee Circuit in Alabama
1893 Ordained deacon by Bishop Isaac W. Joyce
1895 Ordained elder by Bishop John Fletcher Hurst
1899 Graduated from U.S. Grant School of Theology in Chattanooga, Tennessee; Valedictorian
1899-1902 Served as pastor of Simpson Methodist Episcopal Church of Birmingham, Ala.
1903-1939 Secretary of the Alabama Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church
1905-1906 Served as pastor of St. Paul Methodist Episcopal Church of Boaz, Ala.
1906-1911 President of John H. Snead Seminary at Boaz, Ala.
1917-1926 President of Central Holiness University (later John Fletcher College) in Oskaloosa, Iowa
1927-1929 Pastor at St. Paul's Methodist Episcopal Church in Boaz, Ala.
1929-1931 Editor, The Way of Faith
1940 Established Brasher Springs Camp Meeting, Gallant, Alabama
1942 Retired; continued preaching frequently at Brasher Springs Camp Meeting and in various conference churches and camp meetings throughout the country
1971, Jan. 25 Died near Attalla, Ala.
Collection Overview
The John Lakin Brasher Papers, 1857-1993 and undated (bulk 1917-1970) are comprised of church-related and personal correspondence; records of the Iowa Holiness Association; records of the Methodist Episcopal Church, Alabama Conference; religious writings and speeches (including sermons, diaries and manuscripts of published works); printed material (tracts, religious brochures, serials, and hymnals); photographs (including many of camp meetings); transcriptions of tape recordings; legal papers; financial papers; and miscellany. Most material concerns the religious career of John L. Brasher; the Holiness (Sanctification) movement in the Methodist Church, particularly in Alabama; Holiness education and the administration of John H. Snead Seminary in Boaz, Ala.; and Central Holiness University (later John Fletcher College) in University Park, Ia.; and camp meetings in the South, particularly Alabama, and the Midwest. Includes biographies of clergy and accounts of religious and family life in rural north Alabama. Among correspondents are Joseph P. Owens, F. D. Leete, John Paul, and missionaries in Egypt, India, China, and Japan. Contains letters and printed material concerning the separation and reunification of the Methodist Episcopal Church and the Methodist Episcopal Church, South.
Brasher's activities as a minister are documented throughout the collection. The Correspondence and Transcriptions of Tape Recordings Series reveal Brasher's reflections on scripture and provide accounts of congregational reactions to his preaching. Transcripts of his sermons appear in the Writings and Speeches Series, Sermons Subseries as well as in the Transcriptions of Tape Recordings and in some of the published articles (Printed Material Series, Serials Subseries) and manuscripts of his books (Printed Material Series, The Way of Faith). His diaries and correspondence document his travels and his preaching engagements. Numerous invitations to preach and requests for guidance reflect Brasher's leadership role among ministers, missionaries, and church officials. Letters to and from converts regarding their religious experiences and responses to Brasher's preaching and writing are scattered throughout the Correspondence Series.
Brasher's administrative role in religious organizations and in church-affiliated educational facilities is well-represented in the Correspondence Series as well as in the Iowa Holiness Association Series and the Methodist Episcopal Church, Alabama Conference Series. Minutes, reports, and financial records are among the papers of these organizations, reflecting both Brasher's leadership and involvement and the activities of the organizations themselves. The Pictures Series includes some photographs of the schools with which Brasher was associated and of the attending students.
Brasher's career as an author is well-documented, not only in the Writings and Speeches Series, but throughout the collection. The Correspondence Series includes letters to and from his publishers and from editors of various religious serials to which Brasher contributed. The Printed Material Series contains many of these serials with articles by Brasher as well as tracts he wrote.
Throughout the collection, information on church history abounds. The Correspondence Series and the Methodist Episcopal Church, Alabama Conference Series in particular contain letters concerning the rivalry between the Methodist Episcopal Church and the Methodist Episcopal Church, South; and the eventual unification of the two organizations. Conflicts between Fundamentalist and Modernist ideas also appear in the correspondence and in the Printed Material Series.
As Historian of the Alabama Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church, Brasher wrote biographies of preachers, missionaries, and church officials involved in the Holiness Movement. These biographies appear in the Writings and Speeches Series, Biographical Sketches of Colleagues Subseries. Some of these biographies were published in Glimpses: Some Personal Glimpses of Holiness Preachers I Have Known, and with Whom I Have Labored in Evangelism, Who Have Answered to Their Names in the Roll Call of the Skies. Manuscripts of some of those appearing in the published work can be found in the Glimpses Subseries. Some of the letters and questionnaires from which Brasher wrote his sketches appear in the Methodist Episcopal Church, Alabama Conference Series, Biographical Information Subseries. The letters from which his information was gleaned vary in degree of detail, with some providing only dates and places of birth, marriage, ordination, etc.; and others giving descriptions of incidents in the religious life of the subject.
Correspondence, Pictures, Transcriptions of Tape Recordings, and the Family Biography Subseries of the Writings and Speeches Series document Brasher's life with his family. Brasher's biographical writings and other works in the Family Biography Subseries, and the Transcriptions of Tape Recordings Series also provide a small but rich glimpse into the traditional lore, customs, and folkways of the rural upland South.
Details of camp meetings are documented throughout the collection. The Transcripts of Tape Recordings Series contains transcripts of camp meetings. The Printed Material Series includes promotional literature for camp meetings; descriptions of facilities; and hymnals (some shape-note) used in these services. An unusual collection of copies of photographs of camp meetings from the early 1900's through the 1940's in Ohio, Iowa, Alabama, Michigan, Texas and Pennsylvania can be found in the Pictures Series.
The Boatman Family Papers, also housed in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, contains correspondence from John Lakin Brasher and other members of the Brasher family.
Subject Headings
Methodist Episcopal Church -- Alabama; Methodist Episcopal Church, South; Methodist Episcopal Church -- Clergy -- Biography; Methodist Episcopal Church -- Sermons; Central Holiness University; John H. Snead Seminary; Iowa Holiness Association; John Fletcher College; Holiness churches -- Education; Holiness churches -- Clergy -- Biography; Holiness churches -- Sermons; Holiness churches -- Alabama; Camp meetings; Evangelistic work -- History; Missionaries -- Correspondence; Sanctification; Preaching -- History; Methodist Church -- Periodicals; Shape note hymnals; Alabama -- Religious life and customs; Alabama -- Social life and customs; Sermons; Diaries; Tracts; Owens, Joseph Parkes, 1886-; Leete, Frederick Deland, 1866-1958; Paul, John H. (John Haywood), 1877-1967
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1857-1993 and undated (bulk 1917-1970)
  Handwritten and typed letters to and from Brasher concerning church business, personal business, family news, and the administration of John H. Snead Seminary and Central Holiness University. Arranged chronologically. The new accession includes many letters to/from John Lakin Brasher to James H. Brasher. The letters provide a snapshot of James' early life, his school work at Central Holiness University, on Altheia, and his social life. Later letters focus on James' career in the ministry. Other family members also figure greatly in the letters: Minnie, Leona, Luther, Eunice, Julius, friends, and brothers and sisters in the ministry. The letters continue unabated until John Lakin Brasher's death in 1971. Also includes restricted material, mainly correspondence between Minnie Moore Brasher and John Lakin Brasher, as well as other family members.
  - 1857-1916, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1917-1918, (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1919-1920, July, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1920, Aug.-1921, Mar. 18, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1921, Mar. 19-1921, June 10, (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1921, June 11-1921, Nov., (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1921, Dec.-1922, Apr., (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1922, May-1922, Oct., (6 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1922, Nov.-1923, Mar., (8 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1923, Apr.-Sept., (8 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1923, Oct.-1924, Feb. 6, (6 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1924, Feb. 18-1924, May 15, (7 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1924, May 16-1924, Oct., (7 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1924, Nov.-1925, May, (7 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1925, June-Dec., (8 folders) (Box 15)
  - 1926, Jan.-Nov. 15, (9 folders) (Box 16)
  - 1926, Nov. 17-1927, Oct., (8 folders) (Box 17)
  - 1927, Nov.-1928, Oct., (7 folders) (Box 18)
  - 1928, Nov.-1929, Aug., (8 folders) (Box 19)
  - 1929, Sept.-1930, Mar. 7, (8 folders) (Box 20)
  - 1930, Mar. 11-1931, Oct., (7 folders) (Box 21)
  - 1931, Nov.-1932, Dec., (6 folders) (Box 22)
  - 1933, Jan.-1934, July, (7 folders) (Box 23)
  - 1934, Aug.-1935, Dec., (6 folders) (Box 24)
  - 1936, Jan.-1937, Feb., (6 folders) (Box 25)
  - 1937, Mar.-1938, Aug., (7 folders) (Box 26)
  - 1938, Sept.-1939, Dec., (7 folders) (Box 27)
  - 1940, Jan.-1942, July, (6 folders) (Box 28)
  - 1942, Aug.-1946, June, (7 folders) (Box 29)
  - 1946, July-1950, Dec., (7 folders) (Box 30)
  - 1951, Jan.-1953, Aug., (7 folders) (Box 31)
  - 1953, Sept.-1955, Aug., (6 folders) (Box 32)
  - 1955, Sept. 1959, Apr., (5 folders) (Box 33)
  - 1959, May-1959, Dec. (2 folders, 1 envelope) (Box 34)
  - 1960, Jan.-1962, Sept. 10, (6 folders) (Box 35)
  - 1962, Sept. 12-1964, Dec., (6 folders) (Box 36)
  - 1965, Jan.-1966, Dec., (5 folders) (Box 37)
  - 1967, Jan.-1968, June, (7 folders) (Box 38)
  - 1968, July-1969, Aug., (8 folders) (Box 39)
  - 1969, Sept.-1993, Dec. and undated, (8 folders) (Box 40)
  - Undated and empty envelopes, (5 folders) (Box 74)
  - Restricted Correspondence, 1879-1964 and undated (Box 75)
    The majority of the letters are from John Lakin Brasher (papa) to Minnie Brasher (mama). Other family members also figure prominently: James and Joy, Luther, Leona, Elizabeth, Julius, Eunice amongst many others. But letters to/from family friends and other congregants are also present. The geographical origins of the letters vary from Jamestown, N.D. to London, K.Y. to Ozark, A.L. to Attala, A.L., as John Lakin Brasher traveled for his various ministry engagements. The subject of the frequent letters (sent several times a week) often focused on health, the farm, the weather, family news, business opportunities, and occasionally, politics. Also included are letters of condolence for Ruby and Johnny. Newspaper clippings were often also attached to letters.
    Publication of this addition requires special permission until Dec 31, 2023.
    - 1879, Oct. 24-1903, Dec. 28 (Box 75)
    - 1905, Jan. 19-1914, Aug. 3 (Box 75)
    - 1915, Mar. 2-1917, Dec. 28 (Box 75)
    - 1918, Feb. 1-1918, Dec. 13 (Box 75)
    - 1919, Mar. 14-1920, Nov. 10 (Box 75)
    - 1921, Jan. 1-1921, Dec. 31 (Box 75)
    - 1922, Jan. 11-1922, Dec. 6 (Box 76)
    - 1923, Jan. 6-1923, Dec. 13 (Box 76)
    - 1924, Jan. 12-1924, Dec. 6 (Box 76)
    - 1925, Jan. 1-1925, June 30 (Box 76)
    - 1925, July 3-1925, Dec. 11 (Box 76)
    - 1926, Jan. 6-1926, Apr. 23 (Box 77)
    - 1926, May 9-1926, June 29 (Box 77)
    - 1926, July 1-1926, July 31 (Box 77)
    - 1926, Aug. 2-1926, Sept. 30 (Box 77)
    - 1926, Oct. 1-1926 Dec. 10 (Box 77)
    - 1927, Jan. 16-1927, Apr. 29 (Box 78)
    - 1927, May 2-1927, Sept. 30 (Box 78)
    - 1927, Oct. 3-1927, Dec. 2 (Box 78)
    - 1928, Jan. 16-1928, Dec. 1 (Box 78)
    - 1929, Feb. 17-1930, Sept. 16 (Box 78)
    - 1931, Jan. 4-1931, Dec. 31 (Box 78)
    - 1932, Jan. 2-1932, Dec. 14 (Box 79)
    - 1933, Jan. 2-1933, Nov. 12 (Box 79)
    - 1934, June 2-1934, Dec. 4 (Box 79)
    - 1934, Jan. 1-1934 May 31 (Box 79)
    - 1935, Jan. 1-1935, Aug. 24 (Box 80)
    - 1935, Sept. 7-1935, Dec. 13 (Box 80)
    - 1936, Jan. 2-1936, July 24 (Box 80)
    - 1936, Aug. 6-1936, Dec. 19 (Box 80)
    - 1937, Jan. 5-1937, Aug. 26 (Box 80)
    - 1937, Sept. 2-1937, Dec. 11 (Box 80)
    - 1938, Jan. 4-1938, Dec. 31 (Box 81)
    - 1939, Jan. 4-1939, Sept. 24 (Box 81)
    - 1939, Oct. 2-1939, Dec. 22 (Box 81)
    - 1940, Jan. 1-1940, Dec. 5 (Box 81)
    - 1941, Mar. 26-1941, Nov. 14 (Box 81)
    - 1942, Jan. 11-1942, Nov. 20 (Box 81)
    - 1943, Feb. 17-1943, June 2 (Box 82)
    - 1943, June 3-1943, Nov. 24 (Box 82)
    - 1944, May 1-1945, Dec. 8 (Box 82)
    - 1946, Jan. 9-1946, Dec. 23 (Box 82)
    - 1947, Jan. 1-1947, Dec. 30 (Box 82)
    - 1948, Feb. 25-1952, Oct. 20 (Box 82)
    - 1953, Nov. 18-1960, Dec. 26 (Box 82)
    - 1961, Feb. 2-1964, July 17 (Box 83)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 83)
    - Empty envelopes (Box 83)
    - Miscellaneous items, 1903-1944, bulk undated (Box 83)
      Includes clippings, receipts, notes, commencement announcements, recipes
- Iowa Holiness Association Series, 1920-1922 and undated
  Papers of the Iowa Holiness Association during Brasher's term as president of the organization. Divided into four subseries: Auxiliary Reports, Correspondence, Financial Papers, and Miscellaneous.
  - Auxiliary Reports Subseries, 1921-1922 and undated
    Reports from local auxiliaries to the Iowa Holiness Association. Most reports are handwritten on printed forms and provide names of officers, dues collected, and numbers of members. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1921, May-1922, May and undated (Box 41)
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1920-1922 and undated
    Original letters and copies to and from Brasher chiefly concerning the organization of camp meetings. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1920, June-1922, Sept. and undated, (3 folders) (Box 41)
  - Financial Papers Subseries, 1920-1922 and undated
    Monthly financial reports, contracts for advertising, and invoices for materials purchased. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1920, June-1922, June and undated (Box 41)
  - Miscellaneous Iowa Holiness Association Material, 1921-1922 and undated
    Includes advertisement for camp meeting, list of camp meetings, a Statement of Doctrine for the Iowa Holiness Association, and a revision to the bylaws of the Iowa Holiness Association. Arranged chronologically
    - 1921-1922 and undated (Box 41)
- Methodist Episcopal Church, Alabama Conference Series, 1867-1943 and undated
  Records of the activities of the Alabama Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church. Includes biographical sketches of conference ministers and church officers and historical information about individual churches collected by Brasher from 1934 to 1936 while he served as historian for the conference. Divided into the following subseries: Annual Conference Minutes; Biographical Information; Church History; District and Charge Statistics; and Certificates and Licenses.
  - Annual Conference Minutes Subseries, 1867-1928.
    Typed copies of the proceedings of the Alabama Annual Conferences. Minutes from some years are not included. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1867-1928 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 42)
  - Biographical Information Subseries, 1934-1936 and undated
    Biographies, varying in length and detail, of ministers and church officers within the Alabama conference. Many were handwritten on a printed questionnaire while some are handwritten in narrative form. Arranged chronologically by last name of the respondent.
    - A-W, (2 folders) (Box 42)
  - Church History Subseries, undated
    Church histories, chiefly handwritten, of individual Methodist churches in Alabama. Includes a typed history of the Alabama Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church written by Brasher in 1936. Arranged alphabetically by the name of the church.
    - A-G (Box 42)
  - District and Charge Statistics Subseries, 1931 and undated
    Statistical information regarding membership, baptism, property, and collections for Methodist churches in Alabama. Pages are numbered, although many pages are missing, and are arranged in numeric order.
    - 1931 and undated (Box 42)
  - Certificates and Licenses Subseries, 1889-1943
    Documents, chiefly issued to Brasher, granting him license to preach and perform holy ordinances and certifying his appointment to church offices. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1889-1943 (Box 42)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1890's-1968 and undated
  Works generally on religious and church-related topics, chiefly written by Brasher. Includes both published work and unpublished writings. Personal diaries and family histories and biographies of individual Brasher family members are also included. Divided into the following subseries: General Writings and Speeches by Brasher; Sermons and Sermon Notes; Diaries; Biographical Sketches of Colleagues; Family Biography; Glimpses; The Way of Faith; Tribute and Some Other Writings and Miscellaneous.
  - General Writings and Speeches Subseries, 1890's-1968 and undated
    Speeches and addresses chiefly delivered by Brasher to the General Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church and other religious groups; and to organizations within John H. Snead Seminary and Central Holiness University and other educational institutions. Includes editorials and inspirational essays from religious publications. Marginalia indicates that some of these articles were also presented as speeches. Also includes chapel lectures given at God's Bible School, Cincinnati, O.H. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1890's-1943, (12 folders) (Box 43)
    - 1946-1968 and undated, (12 folders) (Box 44)
    - N.D., (5 folders) (Box 45)
  - Sermons and Sermon Notes Subseries, 1892-1968 and undated
    Sermons and notes for sermons, typed and handwritten, by Brasher and others. Some copies. Sermons by Brasher and sermons by others arranged chronologically in separate sequences.
    - Brasher's Sermons, 1924-1928 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 46)
    - Sermons by Others, 1900-1964, (2 folders) (Box 46)
  - Diaries Subseries, 1922-1968
    Bound, handwritten diaries in which Brasher recorded ideas and daily activities. There are no diaries for some years. Also includes James Brasher's daylogue from 1922-1924. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1922-1946, (14 volumes) (Box 47)
    - 1947-1958, (13 volumes) (Box 48)
    - 1959-1968, (12 volumes) (Box 49)
  - Biographical Sketches of Colleagues Subseries, 1906-1965, undated
    Short biographies of ministers, church members, and religious educators, chiefly written by Brasher. Sketches vary in length and detail, and a few include memorial poetry. Many undated. Arranged alphabetically by last name of subject.
    - A-T, (2 folders) (Box 50)
  - Family Biography Subseries, 1897-1966 and undated
    Biographies of Brasher family members, many written by Brasher in memory of deceased relatives. Includes autobiographies by Brasher. Biographies vary in length and detail. Works by Brasher are arranged chronologically by the date of writing. Works by others are arranged chronologically by date of writing in a separate folder. Includes copy of Giant of a Century Trail, a biography of Brasher written by Jon Tal Murphree in 1969.
    - Family Biography by Brasher, 1895-1966 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 50)
    - Family Biography by Others, 1921-1961 and undated (Box 50)
    - Giant of a Century Trail, by Jon Tal Murphree (1969) (Box 50)
  - Glimpses Subseries, ca. 1954.
    Fragments of drafts and notes for Brasher's biographical work, Glimpses: Some Personal Glimpses of Holiness Preachers Whom I Have Known, and With Whom I Have Labored in Evangelism, Who Have Answered to Their Names in the Roll Call of the Skies (1954). Includes typescripts with marginalia and handwritten drafts. Each fragment is arranged in order of the page numbers assigned by Brasher. Material is undated.
    - Introduction, (3 folders) (Box 51)
    - Introduction and fragment (Box 51)
    - Draft (Box 51)
    - Fragment with notations (Box 51)
    - Fragments, (3 folders) (Box 51)
  - The Way of Faith Subseries, 1930-1931 and undated
    Editorials and Sunday school lessons handwritten by Brasher for publication in The Way of Faith and Neglected Themes, a serial for which he served as editor. (For copies of the newsletter in this collection, see Printed Material: Serials). Arranged chronologically.
    - Editorials: 1930-1931 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 51)
    - Sunday School Lessons: 1930-1931, (2 folders) (Box 51)
  - Tribute and Some Other Writings, by John L. Brasher, 1926 (volume)
    Published volume of memorial writings by Brasher. Most chapters concern deceased family members and fellow church officials.
    - Tribute and Some Other Writings, 1926 (volume) (Box 51)
  - Miscellaneous Writings Subseries, 1901-1972 and undated
    Poetry and articles written by people other than Brasher. Most concern inspirational subjects. Some copies. Arranged chronologically.
    - 1901-1972 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 52)
- Printed Material Series, 1883-1973 and undated
  Printed material, chiefly concerning religious topics, collected by Brasher. Divided into the following subseries: Serials; Pamphlets; Tracts; Hymnals; Yearbooks; Clippings; Camp Meetings; Promotional Literature; Programs; Reports and Newsletters; Railway Timetables; and Miscellaneous Printed Material.
  - Serials Subseries, 1910-1971.
    Religious serials. Arranged by title, then chronologically for each publication. Issues are not sequential for all titles.
    - American Holiness Journal, 1950, Feb.-1955, July (Box 53)
    - American Holiness Journal, 1955, Sept.-1969, Sept. (Box 54)
    - Call to Prayer, 1941-1969 (Box 55)
    - Central Holiness University Bulletin, 1923-1928 (Box 55)
    - Christian Faith and Life, 1931, Mar.-1933, Feb. (Box 55)